Edward Bruce
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Correspondence, circa 1921-1957, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-6; 5.5 linear feet)
  - Alphabetical Correspondence, circa 1921-1957, Subseries 2.1:
    - Martin, David Stone, 1942, (Reel D87:709-717) (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - May, Stacy, 1940-1941, (Reel D87:911-920) (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Mellett, Lowell, 1934-1941, (Reel D87:921-960) (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Milch Galleries, 1932-1941, (5 folders; Reel D87:961-1164) (Box 3, Folder 55-59)
    - Millier, Arthur, 1933-1940, (Reel D88:58-83) (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Minor, Pearl, 1934-1938, (Reel D87:753-760) (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Mittell, Sherman F., 1936-1941, (Reel D87:761-773) (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Morgan, Forbes, 1934-1936, (2 folders; Reel D87:1165-1224) (Box 3, Folder 63-64)
    - Morgenthau, Henry & Mrs., 1937-1941, (4 folders; Reel D85:984-1169) (Box 3, Folder 65-68)
    - Mount Rushmore Project, 1925-1939, undated, (7 folders; Reel D87:1225-1498) (Box 3, Folder 69-75)
    - Munn, John R., 1935-1936, (Reel D87:1499-1506) (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Murphy, Frank, 1938-1940, (Reel D87:1507-1519) (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Museum of Fine Arts of Houston, 1930-1931, (Reel D87:1520-1524) (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Museum of Modern Art, 1938-1941, (2 folders; Reel D87:1525-1589) (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
    - N, Miscellaneous, 1933-1941, (Reel D87:1597-1649) (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - National Academy of Design, 1935-1942, (2 folders; Reel D87:1650-1729) (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
    - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, 1935, 1941-1942, (Reel D87:1590-1596) (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - National Gallery of Art, 1939-1941, (Reel D87:1730-1734) (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - National Institute of Arts and Letters, 1939-1942, (Reel D87:1735-1740; D88:1-15) (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Neumann, J. B., 1937-1941, (Reel D87:1600-1611) (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - News Correspondents, 1935-1942, (Reel D88:16-57) (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Nichols, William B., 1936, (Reel D87:1622-1639) (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - O, Miscellaneous, 1932-1941, (Reel D88:84-104) (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - P, Miscellaneous: Pa-Pe, 1934-1942, (Reel D88:116-162) (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - P, Miscellaneous: Pf-Pu, 1934-1941, (Reel D88:163-202) (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Parrott, Fred & Adelaide Annette, 1938-1940, undated, (Reel D88:122-138) (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Parsons, William E., 1934-1938, (Reel D88:203-215) (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Peirce, Waldo, 1936-1941, (Reel D88:216-244) (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Peoples, C. J., 1935-1940, (Reel D88:245-257) (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Philippine Sugar Association, 1933-1937, (2 folders; Reel D88:364-441) (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
    - Phillips Memorial Gallery, 1937-1942, (Reel D88:442-462) (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Pittman, Key, 1932-1935, (Reel D88:463-483) (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - P. M. Magazine, 1940-1941, (Reel D88:105-115) (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Poland, William B., 1936-1942, undated, (Reel D88:484-506) (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Poor, Henry Varnum, 1937-1942, (Reel D88:507-563) (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Porter, William R., 1936, (Reel D88:181-187) (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Purdon, Eric, 1934-1939, (Reel D88:564-589) (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - R, Miscellaneous: Re-Roo, 1932-1942, (Reel D88:590-642) (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - R, Miscellaneous: Ros-Ru, 1932-1941, (Reel D88:643-664) (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Radio Broadcast, National Broadcasting Company, 1940, (3 folders; Reel D88:665-774) (Box 4, Folder 31-33)
    - Radio Broadcast fan mail, 1940, (2 folders; Reel D88:781-863) (Box 4, Folder 34-35)
    - Reed, Horace E., 1929-1941, (4 folders; Reel D88:864-1011) (Box 4, Folder 36-39)
    - Reinhardt Galleries, 1929-1931, (Reel D88:1012-1037) (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Reynolds, Jackson E., 1929-1939, (3 folders; Reel D88:1038-1117) (Box 4, Folder 41-43)
    - Robert, Lawrence Wood, 1933-1940, (2 folders; Reel D88:1118-1196) (Box 4, Folder 44-45)
    - Robinson, Boardman, 1935-1940, (2 folders; Reel D88:1197-1254) (Box 4, Folder 46-47)
    - Robinson, Joseph T., 1932, 1936, (Reel D88:603-610) (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Roosevelt, President Franklin D., 1934-1942, (7 folders; Reel D90:207-490) (Box 4, Folder 49-55)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1933-1942, (5 folders; Reel D90:491-707) (Box 4, Folder 56-60)
    - Roosevelt, Henry L., 1935-1936, (Reel D88:624-634) (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Rosenberg, James N., 1934-1937, (Reel D88:1255-1271) (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Rowan, Edward, 1934-1944, (9 folders; Reel D88:1272-1651) (Box 4, Folder 63-71)
    - S, Miscellaneous, 1932-1942, undated, (Reel D88:1652-1687) (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Sample, Paul, 1934-1940, undated, (Reel D88:1688-1734) (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Schaub, Lincoln F., 1935-1940, undated, (2 folders; Reel D88:1735-1818) (Box 4, Folder 74-75)
    - Section of Fine Arts Luncheon for Mrs. Roosevelt, 1941, (2 folders; Reel D90:43-192) (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - Serva, Albert E., 1933, (Reel D89:71-73) (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Shankar, Sir Girja, 1942, (Reel D82:344-351) (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Silver Value, 1933-1934, (Reel D89:74-100) (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Soong, T. V., 1941, (Reel D89:101-103) (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Stack, Theo. M., 1933, (Reel D89:233-247) (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Stackpole, Ralph, 1939-1942, (Reel D89:248-277) (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Stein, Leo, 1932-1942, 1950, undated, (7 folders; Reel D89:278-623) (Box 5, Folder 9-15)
    - Sterne, Maurice, 1931-1934, (Reel D89:624-665) (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Saint Louis Art Museum, 1933, (Reel D89:666-669) (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Stone, Harlan F., 1932-1942, (5 folders; Reel D89:670-930) (Box 5, Folder 18-22)
    - Stone, Julius F., Jr., 1934-1942, (6 folders; Reel D89:931-1161) (Box 5, Folder 23-28)
    - Studio House, 1935-1938, (Reel D89:1162-1173) (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Sullivan, Frank E., 1933, (Reel D89:1174-1179) (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Sutro, Oscar, 1933-1934, (Reel D89:1180-1229) (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Switzer, John M., 1933-1934, (Reel D89:1230-1247) (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - T, Miscellaneous: Ta-Ti, 1935-1940, (Reel D89:1248-1291) (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - T, Miscellaneous: To-Ty, 1932-1941, (Reel D89:1292-1314) (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Taylor, Francis Henry, 1933-1938, (Reel D89:1251-1259) (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Thomas, Elbert, 1941-1942, (Reel D89:1331-1340) (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - John L. Thompson, Sons & Co., Inc., 1934, (Reel D89:1269-1277) (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Thurston, Elliott, 1935-1940, (Reel D89:1341-1364) (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Tilney, Frederick, 1935-1936, (Reel D89:1281-1287) (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Time Incorporated, 1932-1942, (Reel D89:1365-1382) (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Treasury Department, Section of Painting and Sculpture, 1934-1939, (2 folders; Reel D89:1-70) (Box 5, Folder 41-42)
    - Treasury Relief Art Project, 1935, (Reel D89:1383-1439) (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Tugwell, Rexford, 1933-1939, (Reel D89:1440-1466) (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - U, Miscellaneous, 1934-1940, (Reel D89:1467-1483) (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - V, Miscellaneous, 1923-1941, (Reel D89:1484-1521) (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - W, Miscellaneous, 1932-1941, undated, (Reel D89:1522-1553; D90:1-4) (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Waldo, Richard H., 1932, (Reel D90:26-34) (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Waldorf-Astoria Hotel, 1933-1937, (Reel D89:1529-1538) (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Walker, Frank, 1933, 1935, (Reel D90:35-38) (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Walter, Edgar, 1933-1938, (Reel D90:39-42) (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Washington Philatelic Society, 1938, (Reel D90:204-206) (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - White House, 1937-1942, (Reel D90:721-728) (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1932-1941, (2 folders; Reel D90:729-796) (Box 5, Folder 54-55)
    - Wiggin, Albert H., 1932-1937, (Reel D90:797-811) (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Williams, Mary L. (Post Office Department), 1940-1941, (Reel D90:812-821) (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Woodward, Robert S., 1934-1942, (Reel D90:822-851) (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Yau, C. F., 1933, 1941-1942, (Reel D90:852-885) (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Letters of Condolence, A-Z, 1943, (15 folders; Reel D90:973-1624) (Box 5, Folder 60-74)
  - Chronological Correspondence, circa 1928-1942, Subseries 2.2:
    Chronological correspondence includes personal and professional correspondence of a more general nature, arranged by date. Many of the same topics covered in the alphabetical correspondence are also found here and include letters of appreciation, updates from friends, and general business and financial matters. The chronological correspondence also includes many of the same correspondents as above. The order of the correspondence on microfilm has been maintained.
    - Chronological Correspondence, undated, 1928-1933, (8 folders; Reel D82:1288-1529; D83:1-96) (Box 6, Folder 1-8)
    - Chronological Correspondence, 1934-1939, (9 folders; Reel D83:97-510) (Box 6, Folder 9-17)
    - Chronological Correspondence, 1940-1942, (7 folders; Reel D83:511-863) (Box 6, Folder 18-24)
- Writings, circa 1931-1942, Series 3:; (Box 6; 0.3 linear feet)
  This series contains four office diaries from 1942, notebooks, and speeches. Most of the diary entries are written by his secretary. The notebooks contain addresses and various notes; one contains lists of Section of Fine Arts projects and artists, and another contains detailed notes and dated entries about his political work for Philippine independence. Also found in this series are written speeches Edward Bruce gave at public events. Most focus on or promote public art projects and programs. A few address other political issues, such as Philippine idependence. Included is a notebook of various speeches, arranged in its original collation.
  The Writings series is arranged into 2 subseries:
  Subseries 3.1: Diaries and Notebooks, circa 1931-1932, 1942
  Subseries 3.2: Speeches, circa 1934-1941
  - Diaries and Notebooks, circa 1931-1932, 1942, Subseries 3.1:
    - Diaries, 1942, (4 diaries, Reel D83:927-1034) (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - "Notebook of Edward Bruce: Addresses and Miscellaneous Notes", circa 1932, (Reel D91:73-152) (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Notebook, "Section of Fine Arts Projects", undated, (Reel D91:1-72) (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Notebook, "Senate 1931 Re: Philippine Independence", 1931, (Reel D88:263-343) (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Speeches, circa 1934-1941, Subseries 3.2:
    - "New Frontiers," undated, (Reel D89:209-220) (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - "The Philippine Problem and the Hawes-Cutting Bill", undated, (Reel D91:165-184) (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - American Federation of Arts Convention, undated, (Reel D89:106-112) (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Home of Under Secretary of State, 1934, (Reel D89:221-232) (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Friedsam Award Ceremony, 1938, (Reel D89:183-186) (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - White House Lecture, 1938, (Reel D89:187-208) (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Cabinet Meeting, 1938-1939, (Reel D89:152-182) (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Exhibit Opening at Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1939, (Reel D89:131-145) (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Section of Fine Arts Luncheon for Mrs. Roosevelt, 1941, (Reel D89:115-124) (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches, 1939-1940, undated, (Reel D89:104-105, 113-114, 125-130, 146-151) (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Notebook of Speeches, 1934-1940, (5 folders; Reel D91:1004-1115) (Box 6, Folder 39-43)
- Financial Material, 1909-1913, 1928-1943, Series 4:; (Box 6, 0.3 linear feet)
  Edward Bruce's financial material is scattered and includes an account book, a cash book, financial records and leases for houses, income tax records, insurance records, and bills for various personal expenditures. Also found are the will and other related estate documents for Isabella Bruce, a relative of Edward Bruce, and a memorandum about the condition of the silver market from a 1933 economic conference. Items are arranged alphabetically by type of records and chronologically within folders.
  - Account Book, undated, (Reel D91:185-188) (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Cashbook for Christmas Party, 1941, (Reel D84:1064-1082) (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Florence House Financial Records, 1934, (Unfilmed) (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Income Tax Records, 1928-1941, (8 folders; partially filmed Reel D90:903-923) (Box 6, Folder 47-54)
  - Income Tax Records, Tax Errors, 1938-1940, (Unfilmed) (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Insurance Records, New England Mutual, 1931-1942, (2 folders; Reel D87:1-60) (Box 6, Folder 56-57)
  - Insurance Records, New York Life, 1912, 1933-1942, (3 folders; Reel D87:61-176) (Box 6, Folder 58-60)
  - Insurance Records, Sun Life Assurance Company of Canada, 1913, 1931-1943, (2 folders; Reel D87:177-245) (Box 6, Folder 61-62)
  - Last Will and Testament of Isabella R. Bruce, 1909, 1917, (Partially filmed Reel D90:924-929, 932) (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Lease of House in Warrenton, Virginia, 1933, (Reel D90:193-203) (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Memorandum on the Silver Market, 1933, (Reel D90:933-944) (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Paid Bills, 1933-1937, (Reel D82:1052-1054, D90:886-902) (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Telephone Bills, 1933-1934, (Reel D82:1315-1330) (Box 6, Folder 67)
- Printed Material, circa 1919, circa 1926-1943, 1960, Series 5:; (Box 7, 0.5 linear feet)
  Printed material documents a wide range of topics including Edward Bruce's career as an artist and as director of the Section of Fine Arts, and other art and government affairs. Included are news clippings and art magazines, brochures from art organizations, and catalogs for exhibitions of Bruce's artwork and others. Also found are published bulletins by the Section of Fine Arts, published speeches from various events on international relations, and other miscellaneous pamphlets, newsletters, and government publications. Materials are arranged alphabetically by type of material and chronologically within each folder.
  - Art Magazines, 1933, 1941, 1943, 1960, (Unfilmed) (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Brochures, 1935-1945, (Unfilmed) (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Bulletin of Section of Painting and Sculpture, 1935, (Reel D91:790-795) (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Bulletin of Treasury Department Art Projects, 1937-1941, (3 folders; Reel D91:769-1003) (Box 7, Folder 4-6)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1926-1939, undated, (Unfilmed) (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Massachusetts: A Guide to Its Places and People, 1937, (Unfilmed) (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - National Institute of Arts and Letters: Constitution and List of Members, 1938, (Unfilmed) (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - News Clippings, 1926-1944, undated, (13 folders; Reel D83:1526-1673; D84:1-118) (Box 7, Folder 10-22)
  - Published Speeches by Others, 1934-1942, (Unfilmed) (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Reproductions of Artwork, undated, (Unfilmed) (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Spruce, a Publication of the Spruce Production Division, circa 1919, (Unfilmed) (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1933-1939, undated, (Unfilmed) (Box 7, Folder 26)
- Scrapbooks, 1922-1941, Series 6:; (Box 7-8; 0.8 linear feet)
  Four scrapbooks document Edward Bruce's career as a professional artist and as the director of the Section of Fine Arts. The scrapbooks include newspaper and magazine clippings, letters, photographs, exhibition invitations and catalogs, and other miscellaneous printed material. Except for a few duplicate items, most of the documents in the scrapbooks are not found elsewhere in the collection. Scrapbook 2 has been unbound but is arranged in its original collation.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1922-1930, (Reel D91:263-391) (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1933-1934, 1938-1939, (5 folders; Reel D91:523-653) (Box 7, Folder 27-31)
  - Scrapbook 3, 1933-1935, 1937-1937, (Reel D91:392-522) (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 4, 1935-1941, (Reel D91:654-789) (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Photographs, circa 1902-1943, Series 7:; (Box 7, 9-10; 1.0 linear foot)
  This series includes Edward and Peggy Bruce's personal photographs and photographs of Bruce's artwork. There are many professional portraits of Bruce, two photos of him painting outdoors, photos of Bruce with wife Peggy, and photographs of the Bruces with friends, including Leo Stein and Maurice Sterne. Also found are photographs of Edward Bruce at special events and government affairs, including a photo of him at an art opening with Eleanor Roosevelt. There are many group photos of Bruce with various individuals, including John Dewey, Henry Morgenthau, Jr., Robert La Follette, Carl Milles, and William Zorach. Also included are numerous travel photographs of China, Italy, and Java. There are numerous photographs of their time in Anticoli Carrado, Italy. Two photograph albums contain photographs taken by Edward Bruce and organized by subject, including boats, houses, animals, trees, and other landscape features. Miscellaneous photographs include friends, houses, and unidentified snapshots. Personal photographs are arranged by subject and chronologically within each folder.
  Photographs of Artwork include black and white photographs of paintings by Edward Bruce. Almost all of the photographs are undated and are in no specific arrangement. Also found is a photograph album of artwork that has been unbound but is arranged in its original collation.
  Researchers should note that the arrangement of the photographs does not match the order of the material on microfilm. However, most of the photographs can be found on reel D83, frames 1212-1535.
  Photographs are arranged into 2 subseries:
  Subseries 7.1: Personal Photographs, circa 1902-1943
  Subseries 7.2: Photographs of Artwork, circa 1926-1935
  - Personal Photographs, circa 1902-1943, Subseries 7.1:
    - Portraits of Edward Bruce, 1902-1915, 1917, undated, (4 folders) (Box 7, Folder 32-35)
    - Edward Bruce Painting Outdoors, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - Edward and Peggy Bruce, 1935, undated (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Edward and Peggy Bruce with Friends, 1925-1937, undated (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Edward Bruce at Special Events, 1941, undated (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Section of Fine Arts Christmas Party, 1938-1941 (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Hurricane Damage at Brattleboro, Vermont, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Carey Project, Huntington, New York, 1939, (5 folders) (Box 7, Folder 42-46)
    - Radio Broadcast, National Broadcasting Company, 1940, (2 folders; Reel D88:775-780) (Box 7, Folder 47-48)
    - War Department Sculpture Competition, circa 1941 (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - Launching of the S. S. Edward Bruce, 1943, (Reel D90:945-956) (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - Photographs of China, 1916 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 1)
    - Photographs of Italy, circa 1925 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 2)
    - Photographs of Java, undated, (Reel D90:957-972) (Box 9 (hol), Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Photographs, 1934-1939, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9 (hol), Folder 4-5)
    - Photograph Album 1, undated, (2 folders; Reel D91:255-262) (Box 9 (hol), Folder 6-7)
    - Photograph Album 2, undated, (4 folders; Reel D91:189-254) (Box 9 (hol), Folder 8-11)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1926-1935, Subseries 7.2:
    - Photographs of Artwork, 1926-1935, undated, (7 folders) (Box 9 (hol), Folder 12-18)
    - Photographs of Artwork, 1926-1935, undated, (4 folders) (Box 10 (hol), Folder 1-3)
    - Photograph Album of Artwork, undated, (5 folders) (Box 10 (hol), Folder 4-9)